OK.
好
Today we are going to talk about a very
今天我们来讲一个很有意思的算法
interesting algorithm called Quicksort --
快速排序
-- which was invented by Tony Hoare in 1962.
由Tony Hoare在1962年发明
And it has ended up being a really interesting algorithm
在很多方面看来它最终发展为
from many points of view.
一个很有意思的算法
And because of that, it turns out today's lecture
所以今天的课
is going to be both hard and fast.
内容较难 讲的也会较快
If you see the person next to you sleeping,
如果你旁边有同学在睡觉
you will want to say let's get going.
你可以叫醒他 让我们出发吧
It's a divide-and-conquer algorithm.
这是一个分治算法
And it sorts, as they say, in place,
而且它就在原地排序
meaning that
也就是说
it just rearranged the elements where they are.
它就在原来的数据区域内进行重排
That is like insertion sort
就像插入排序一样
rearranges elements where they are.
就在原地完成排序
Mergesort does not. Mergesort requires extra
归并排序就不一样 它需要额外的
storage in order to do the merge operation.
空间来进行归并排序操作
To merge in linear time and place,
为了在线性时间与空间内归并
it doesn't merge in place in linear time.
它不能在线性时间内实现就地排序
It doesn't do it just by rearranging.
原地排序对它来说并不足够
It is nice because it is in place,
而快速排序的优点就在于它是原地的
so that means that
也就是说
it is fairly efficient in its use of storage.
它很节省内存
And it also happens to be very practical
事实上它也很实用
if you tune it a bit.
如果你微调一下的话
The basic algorithm turns out,
这个基础算法表明
if you just implement that,
如果你直接拿来用它
it's not necessarily that efficient.
可能并不那么高效
But if what you do was then
但如果你接下来
take, do the standard kinds of things you do
按照标准的步骤进行一些微调
to goose up the runtime of something,
来改进它的运行时间的话
and we'll talk a little about what those things are,
待会我们会提到怎样改进
then it can be very, very practical.
届时快速排序可以变得非常实用
So, it uses divide-and-conquer paradigm.
因此快速排序采取分治策略
First step is divide.
第一步是分解问题
And to do this basically it does it by partitioning.
本质上快速排序把数据分划成几份
So, it partitions the input array
所以 快速排序通过选取一个关键数据
into two subarrays
再根据它的大小
around an element we call the pivot --
把原数组分成两个子数组
such that elements in the lower
第一个数组里的数都比
subarray are less than or equal to x,
这个主元数据要小
are less than or equal to elements
而另一个数组里的数都
in the upper subarray.
大于或者等于它
If we draw a picture of the input array,
如果我们把输入的数组画出来
this partition step basically takes some element x
这个分划的步骤就是选取某个数据x
and everything over here is less than
然后把所有小于或者等于x的
or equal to x after the partition step
数据都放在这边
and everything over here is greater than or equal to x.
所有大于或等于x的数据都放在那边
And so now the conquer step is pretty easy.
这样一来解决问题的步骤就非常容易
You just recursively sort the two subarrays.
用递归来处理两个子数组的排序就可以了
So, I recursively sort
那么我们用递归排序来处理
the elements less than or equal to x
比x小的数据
I recursively sort
同样的方法
the elements greater than or equal to x.
来处理比x大的数据
And then the combine is then just trivial.
最后把它们联接倒不那么重要
Because once I have sorted
因为一但我把
the things less than or equal to x,
等于或者比x小
then sorted the things greater than or equal to x,
和比x大的数都排好了
the whole thing is sorted.
整个数组里的数据也就排好了序
So, there is nothing to do really for the combine.
所以最后把它们放到一起是小菜一碟
The key step in quicksort is this partition step.
快速排序里面最关键的一步是分划的步骤
That is the thing that does all of the work.
这是这个算法处理问题的核心
And so you can view quicksort
所以你可以把快速排序看成是
as just recursive partitioning.
递归地分划数组
That's all it is.
基本上就是这样
Just as mergesort was recursive merging,
就像合并排序就是递归地合并一样
quicksort sort of goes the other way around
快速排序某种程度走了另一条路
and does recursive partitioning.
也就是递归着分划
The key is the linear time,
当然最重要的是它的复杂度是线性的
by which I mean theta n, partitioning subroutine.
也就是Θ(n)个分划的子程序
And here are some pseudocode for it.
接下来我来写伪代码
This is actually slightly different from the book.
这其实和课本上的稍有不同
The book has one. In fact, there is a nice problem
课后习题里面有个不错的问题
in the book that has even a different one,
其中的伪代码又稍有不同
but they are all basically the same idea.
但它们的原理都一样
This's partition(A, p, q) .
这个partition(A, p, q)函数
And what we are looking at this step of the recursion,
在递归的步骤上来看
is the subarray A from p to q.
处理的是A数组中从p到q的部分
And basically we pick a pivot, which is we're going to
首先我们选一个主元数据
just pick as the first element of the array A of p.
这里我们选了数组的第一个元素p
And the book, just for your information, uses A of q.
课本里稍有不同 选了q
I use A of p. It doesn't really matter.
我们这里用了p 但这其实无关紧要
And then we set an index to p
然后我们设置p的索引
and then we have a loop.
然后是一个循环
This is the code.
这是循环的代码
Basically the structure of it is a for loop
基本的结构就是一个for循环语句
with an "If" Statement in the middle.
中间加上一个if条件语句
And so the structure of the algorithm
这个分划步骤的
of this partitioning step
算法结构可以画出来
looks as follows. We set the pivot
我们先把第一个数据
to be the first element. Here is p and here is q.
选作主元 这里是p 这里是q
This is going to be our invariant for the loop.
这将是我们的循环不变量
And, at any time during the execution of a loop,
那么在运行的过程中
I essentially have some values up to i
数组里比x小的数
which are already less than or equal to x
都被移动到了索引i以前
and then some values that end at j minus 1
而索引i+1到j-1中的数据
that are greater than or equal to x.
就是等于或者比x大的数
And then I don't know about the rest.
j以后的数据 我们还不知道
And so we start out with i equal to p
所以最开始的时候i等于p
and j equal to p plus 1. It starts out at p plus 1
j等于p+1 从p+1开始
so everything is unknown except for x here.
所以除了x其他东西都还是未知
And then the idea is that
那这个循环想要
it is going to preserve this invariant.
保持这个不变量
And the way it does it is, as we go through the loop,
所以在执行的过程中
it looks at a of j
它检查索引j下的数据
and says is it greater than or equal to x
看它是否大于或等于x
Sorry, is it less than or equal to x?
不 应该是核查它是否小于或等于x
If it is greater than or equal to x it does nothing,
那如果这个数据大于或等于x
because what can happen?
那我们什么都不用做了
If this is greater than or equal to x,
如果它等于或比x大
essentially it just goes to the next iterational loop
只用把j这个界限
which moves this boundary
加上1就好了
and the invariant is satisfied. Does everybody see that?
然后循环不变量就满足了 都清楚了吗
Yeah, OK. But if it is less than or equal to x,
好 那如果这个数据小于或者等于x
I have got a problem if I want to maintain the invariant
那我们就得做些什么来维持循环不变量
if this next element is less than or equal to x.
如果这个数据比x小或者等于x
And so what it does then is it says oh,
那它就把索引i+1下的
let me just move this boundary and swap
比x大的数据
this element here, which is gre ater than or equal to x,
和当前的比x小的数据
with this one here that is less than or equal to x,
的位置互换
thereby increasing the size of this subarray
然后再移动界限的位置
and then the invariant is satisfied again.
这样不变量就又被满足了
It is a fairly simple algorithm.
这是个很简单的算法
And it is actually a very tight and easy algorithm.
这事实上是一个很简洁和简单的算法
This's one reason that this's such a great piece of code
这也是为什么这个代码非常漂亮的原因
because it is very efficient.
因为它很高效
Now, in principle, the running time for this
那么这个算法在n个数据下的
on n elements is order n.
运行时间大约是n
Because I am basically
因为它基本上就是
just going through the n elements and
把n个数据过了一遍
just doing a constant amount of work
而每个步骤所需的时间
and then just a constant amount of work outside.
和拼起每个步骤所需的时间都是常数
This is a clever piece of code.
这是一段很好的代码
In fact, in principle partition is easy, right?
事实上 如果我们不考虑原地排序的话
If I weren't worrying about doing it in place,
分划是非常容易的 对吧
it is really a pretty easy thing to do.
我们可以很轻松的就做到
I take an element and
我随便选个数据
just compare every other element with it.
然后和其他每个数据比较
I throw one into one bin and one into the other.
比它大的扔到这一边 小的到另一边
That is clearly linear time.
很明显是线性时间
But often what you find is that just because
但你通常会发现
you can do it that way theoretically doesn't mean that
理论上你能这样做并不意味着
that is going to end up giving you good code.
最终你能够写出好的代码
And this is a nice piece of code
而这是一段非常漂亮的代码
that allows you to do it in place.
让你很好地应用这个算法
And that's one reason why this's a particularly good algorithm,
这也是为什么这个算法很不错的原因
because the constants are good.
因为线性时间的常数不大
So, yes, when we do asymptotic analysis we tend to ignore the constants,
因此我们在做渐进分析时倾向于忽略常数
but when you're actually building code you care about the constants.
但当在写代码的时候你得考虑常数
But first you care much more than just about the constants,
但首先你要考虑的不仅仅是常数
is whether overall it is going to be a fast algorithm.
是这个算法整体上是否足够快
Let's go through an example of this,
那我们来看一个例子
I guess I will do it over here,
在这里
just so we get the gist.
来看看你们有没有领会要点
Here is a sample array that I have created out of hallcloth.
这是我随便写的一个数组
And here we are going to set x, the pivot, to be 6.
主元设为6
Let's look to see how this algorithm works.
那我们来看看这个算法怎样运行
So, i starts out here and j starts out here
i从这开始 j从这开始
if we initialize.
如果我们初始化
And what we do is start scanning right, essentially
然后开始逐个向右扫描
that code is scanning right until it gets something
直到发现一个
which is less than or equal to the pivot.
小或者等于主元的数
It keeps going here until it finds,
j不断的加1
j keeps incrementing until it finds something
直到它发现一个
less than or equal to the pivot.
小于或者等于主元的数
And, in that case, it is the number 5.
在这里这个数就是5
Then it says we will swap these two things.
然后我们把这两个数互换
And it does that and we get
于是我们得到了
6, 5, 13, 10, 8, 3, 2, 11.
6 5 13 10 8 3 2 11
And meanwhile now I gets incremented
同时i加一
and j continueswhere it left off.
j还是在原来的地方
And so now we keep scanning right
然后我们继续往右
until we get to something
直到又遇到一个
that is less than or equal to the pivot.
小于或者等于主元的数
In this case it is 3.
这里就是3
We swap 3 and 5 and get 6, 3, etc.
我们把3和5互换 就得到了6, 3 等等
And now, at this step we increment i,
然后我们再把i加上1
we start j out here.
j从这开始
And in this case, right off the bat,
那在这里我们立刻就看到了一个
we have something which is less than or equal to x,
小于或者等于主元x的数
so we swap these two.
那我们就把它们互换
I blew it, didn't I? Oops. What did I do?
啊 我搞错了 对吧 我哪里做错了
I swapped the wrong thing, didn't I, here?
我换错了数 是不是 这里
That is why I am not a computer.
这是因为我不是一台计算机
Good. We should have swapped this guy, right?
好 我们应该交换这个
Swapped i plus 1, right?
交换i+1 对吗
This was i.
这里是i
We swap I plus 1, good.
交换i+1
So, that's all wrong.
这些都错了
Let's swap the right things.
我们按照正确顺序交换下
Now we have 6, 5, 3, 10, 8, 13, 2, 11.
现在是6 5 3 10 8 13 2 11
That even corresponds to my notes for some strange reason.
这下和我的教案一样了
This is i and now this is j.
这里是i 这里是j
And now when I look, I immediately have something
我们看看这里
that is less than or equal to the pivot.
它小于等于主元
We swap this and i plus 1,
和这里交换 i加上1
so now we have 6, 5, 3, 2, 8, 13, 10, 11.
现在得到6 5 3 2 8 13 10 11
And we, at that point, increment i to here.
将i加1到这里
And we have j now going here and j runs to the end.
j向前进移动 这里j到达末尾
And the loop terminates.
现在循环结束了
When the loop terminates there is one last swap that we do,
当循环结束时我们还要做最后一次交换
which is to put our pivot element in the middle between the two subarrays.
把主元放在两个子串中间
Here we swap this one and this one,
我们交换这个和这个
and so that gives us then 2, 5, 3, 6, 8, 13, 10, 11.
现在得到2 5 3 6 8 13 10 11
And this is the pivot.
这里是主元
And everything over here is less than or equal to the pivot.
左边的数都小于等于主元
And everything over here is greater than or equal to the pivot.
右边的数都大于等于主元
OK, so the quicksort routine.
好了 这就是快速排序的方法
Once we have this partition routine,
当我们知道了分划方法
quicksort is a pretty easy piece of code to write.
快速排序在代码上很容易实现
I should have said return here i, right?
这里应该返回i 对吧
You have got to return with the pivot.
应该要返回主元
Here I have got to return i because
这里要返回i
we want to know where the pivot element is.
因为我们需要知道主元是什么
Sorry.
抱歉
I will plug in my code.
要改改代码了
r gets partition of A,P,Q
r得到A p q分划的结果
and then we quicksort A,P,r-1
接着我们快排两个子串 A p r-1
and quicksort of A,r+1,Q
和 A r+1 q
And that is it. That's the code.
就是这样了 这是实现代码
The initial call is quicksort of A, 1, n.
初始调用快排A 1 n
Because once we partitioned,
因为分划之后
we just have to quicksort the two portions, the left and right portions.
只需要快排两部分 左边和右边的部分
Just the boundary case is probably worth mentioning for a second.
我们需要特别说明一下边界状态
If there are zero or one elements,
如果有0个或1个元素
that is basically what can possibly happen here,
那么在这里将会是
is that I get zero or one elements here.
当这里是0个或1个元素的时候
Then the point is there is nothing to do because the array is sorted,
那么这里就没有工作量
either because it is an empty array
因为数组要么为空
or because it only has one element.
要么只有一个元素
One of the tricks to making quicksort go fast,
一个让快速排序运行更快的方法
as one tunes this, is to, in fact,
是调整这里的代码
look at having a special purpose sorting routine for small numbers of elements.
找到适合元素数目较少时的特别的算法
For example, if you get down to five elements
比如说 最后只剩下5个元素
having some straight line piece of code
你已经知道了一些代码
that knows how to sort five elements sufficiently
来高效地排序5个元素
as opposed to continuing to go through
相对于用这里的递归
recursion in order to accomplish that.
就会好一些
And there are a variety of other things.
还有一些其他的方法
This is a tail recursive code,
这是尾递归的代码
and so you can use certain tail recursion optimizations.
那么就可以使用一些尾递归的优化
And there are a variety of other kinds of optimizations
还有很多优化的方法
that you can use to make this code go fast.
你可以用这些方法使得代码运行更快
So, yeah, you can tune it up a bit
对 你可以做一些修改
beyond what is there, but the core of it is
但是核心部分
this efficient partitioning routine.
是这里的很有效的分划方法
That is the algorithm.
这就是快速排序算法
It turns out that looking at how fast it runs
实际上要得知这个算法运行的速度
is actually a little bit challenging.
是有一些困难的
In the analysis, we are going to assume
在分析中我们假设
that all elements are distinct.
所有的元素都是不同的
It turns out that this particular code
然后当重复元素存在时
does not work very well when you have repeated elements,
代码就运行得不是很好
but Hoare's original partitioning routine
但Hoare最初的分划方法
is actually more efficient in that case
在这种情况下更为高效
if there are duplicates in what you are sorting.
如果待排序的元素中有重复的话
And I encourage you to look at that.
我建议你看看那个方法
It has a much more complicated invariant for partitioning routine,
它使用一个更加复杂的不变量用来实现分划过程
but it does a similar kind of thing.
但本质上是一样的
It's just a bit more complicated.
只是有点复杂而已
If they weren't all distinct, there are things you can do
如果元素有重复的 你可以把重复去掉
to make them distinct or you can just use this code.
或者使用这个代码
The easiest thing to do is just use Hoare's original code
用Hoare的代码是最简单的一种方式
because that works pretty well when they are nondistinct.
当元素有重复的时候 它运行得很好
But this is a little bit easier to understand.
但是这个要相对容易理解些
Let's let T(n) be the worst-case running time
假设T(n)是n个元素
on n elements.
在最差情况下的运行时间
And so what is the worse-case?
最差情况是什么
What is the worse-case going to be for quicksort?
快速排序的最差情况是什么
That's right. If you always pick the pivot
没错 如果你每次都选择这样一个数做主元
and everything is greater than or everything is less than,
其他每个数都比这个数大或者小
you are not going to partition the array very well.
那么分划就不正常了
And when does that happen?
什么时候会发生这种情况
What does the original input look like that makes that happen?
最初的输入数据是什么样子
If it is already sorted or reverse sorted.
如果数据已经排序或者逆序排好了
So, if the input is sorted
如果输入正序排好了
or reverse sorted.
或者逆序排好
That is actually kind of important to understand,
我们需要明白这一点很重要
because it turns out the most common thing to sort is
因为很常见的情况就是
something that is already sorted, surprisingly,
数已经排好序 这很令人吃惊吧
or things that are nearly sorted.
或者几乎要排好
But often it is just sorted
但是通常已经是排好了
and somebody wants to make sure it is sorted.
而人们想要确认是不是排好的办法
Well, let's just sort it again
通常是再排序一次
rather than checking to see if it is sorted.
而不是检查是不是已经排好
And, in those cases, one side of the partition
在那些情况下 分划的一边
of each partition has no elements.
每个分划的一边都没有元素
Then we can write out what the recursion is for that.
我们可以写出这种递归
We have T(n)
对于T(n)
If one side has no elements,
如果分划的一边没有元素
we are going to have T(0) on that side.
那么这一边是T(0)
And on the other side we are going to have T(n-1).
分划的另一边是T(n-1)
We are just writing out the recursion for this.
我们把递归写出来
One side has no elements. The other side has n-1 elements.
一边没有元素 另一边有n-1个元素
And then partitioning and all the bookkeeping and so forth order n.
分划和记录等工作是Θ(n)
What is T(0)?
T(0)是多少
What is T(0)? What is that asymptotically?
T(0)是多少 它趋向于多少
It's a constant, order 1.
常量 Θ(1)
That is just order 1 + T(n-1) + order n.
Θ(1)+T(n-1)+Θ(n)
Well, the order 1 can be absorbed into the order n,
Θ(1)可以算到Θ(n)中去
so this is really just saying it is T(n-1) + order n.
这实际上是T(n-1)+Θ(n)
And what is that equal to?
这等于多少
That is order n^2.
是Θ(n²)
Why is that order n^2?
为什么是Θ(n²)
It is an arithmetic series.
这是一个等差级数
Actually, just like we got for insertion sort.
实际上就像插入排序一样
Just like for insertion sort
就像插入排序一样
it is an arithmetic series.
这是一个等差级数
Going through all that work
我们用快速排序
and we have an algorithm called quicksort,
完成这些工作
and it is no faster than insertion sort.
不比插入排序快
Nevertheless, I said it was a good algorithm.
尽管如此 我说它是个好算法
The reason it is a good algorithm is because
快速排序是个好算法是因为
its average case time,
它的平均情况时间是很好的
as we are going to see, is very good.
这点我们就要看到
But let's try to understand this a little bit more just so that
但是我们先来好好理解下这个
we understand the difference between what is going to happen
然后我们就能看出
in the average case and what is going to happen in the worse-case.
平均情况和最坏情况的差别
Let's draw a recursion tree for this
我们为最差情况画个递归树
for T(n) = T(0) + T(n-1) + and I will make the constant explicit for cn.
T(n)=T(0)+T(n-1)+cn cn展开出来
So, we get an intuition of what is going on.
现在我们知道怎么做了
Some constant times n.
某个常数乘以n
And then we have T(n) is equal to,
T(n)等于
and we write it with the constant part here, cn,
这里的常数部分cn
and then T(0) here,
T(0)在这里
and then T(n-1) here.
T(n-1)在这里
Now, I know that all you folks are really fast
我知道你们这些家伙都算的很快
and want to jump immediately to the full-blown tree.
你们想直接跳到完整的树的底部
But, let me tell you, my advice is
但是我告诉你们 我的建议是
that you spend just a couple of minutes writing it out.
你们花几分钟时间把它写出来
Since the tree grows exponentially,
因为树呈指数级的增长
it only costs you a constant overhead
你只需花一点时间
to write out the small cases and make sure
写出小的情况
that you have got the pattern that you are developing.
并且确保你明白了这个模式
So, I am going to go one more step.
我再做一步
Here we have T(0)
这里是T(0)
and now this becomes c(n-1)
这里是c(n-1)
and now we have another T over here and T.
这里是另外一个T(0)和T(n-2)
And we continue that, dot, dot, dot.
我们接着这样做下去
until  we get to...
直到到达
That is all equal to cn with a T(0) here,
等于cn下面是T(0)
c(n-1) with a T(0),
c(n-1)下面是T(0)
c(n-2)
c(n-2)
T(0) here,
这里是T(0)
and that goes all the way down until we end up with order 1 down here.
这样一直下来直到Θ(1)为止
What is the height of this tree?
树的高度是多少
What is the height of the tree here?
这里树的高度是多少
Yeah, n. Good.
对 n 很好
Because every step we are just decrementing the argument by 1.
因为在每一步我们的参数只减少了1
So, the height is n.
所以 高度为n
To analyze this, let's first add up everything that is here.
为了分析这个问题 我们首先把这里的所有式子相加
Just so we understand where these things are coming from,
刚刚我们分析了这些项是怎么产生的
this is just theta of the summation of k equals 1 to n of k,
这些是 Θ(k从1累加到n的和)
actually of ck.
实际上是ck
That is what is in there.
这就是这里的结果
And that is equal to order n^2.
并且这就等于Θ(n²)
That is where our algorithmatic series is coming from.
这就使我们的算法复杂度如何得到的
And then all of these things here are all Theta(1).
这里的所有项 都是Θ(1)
And how many of them are there?
这里有多少项?
There are n Theta's.
这里有n个Θ(1)
So, the total amount is T(n)=theta(n)+theta(n^2)=theta(n^2)
所以总量是T(n)=Θ(n)+Θ(n²)=Θ(n²)
Just to see what the structure is in terms of the recursion tree,
我们来看根据递归树我们得到了什么样的结构
it is a highly unbalanced recursion tree.
这是一棵高度不平衡的递归树
Now I am going to do something that I told you should never do,
现在我将要分析一个我们以后不会去做的问题
which is we are going to be do a best-case analysis.
我们来分析一下最优情况
This is for intuition only.
这只是为了直观理解
And, in general, we don't do best-case analyses.
通常情况下 我们是不会进行最优情况分析的
It doesn't mean anything,
因为它不会说明任何问题
unless we get some intuition for it maybe.
除非我们需要一些直观的理解
But basically it means nothing mathematically
但是 在数学上它并不能代表任何问题
because it's providing no guarantee.
因为我们无法保证处于最优情况中
And so this is intuition only.
所以这只是为了直观理解
If we are really lucky what happens for partition?
如果我们足够的幸运 分划会发生在什么地方?
What is going to be the lucky case?
什么情况是最幸运的情况?
Yeah, it splits right in the middle.
是的 分划发生在正中央
Which is essentially --
也就是正好在
n/2.
n/2
It is really n/2 : n/2,
这时是n/2:n/2
but we're not going to worry about the details because
在这里我们不过多地考虑细节因为
we're only doing intuition for the best-case because
我们分析最优情况只是为了直观理解 因为
best-case is not what we want.
最优情况并不是我们想要真正分析的
If that happened, what is the recurrence I get?
如果分划发生在正中央 我们会得到怎样的递归式?
Imagine it split it exactly in the middle every time,
想象一下 每一次分划都发生在正中央
then what happens?
会发生什么?
You get T(n) = 2T(n/2) + order n for partitioning and bookkeeping.
可以得到 T(n) = 2T(n/2) 加上分划与合并的复杂度
And what is the solution of that recurrence?
这个递归式的结果是什么?
That is n log n. That is the same as the merge sort recurrence.
是nlgn 也就是和归并排序的结果一样
It is which case of the master theorem?
这是主定理的第几种情况?
Case 2, right?
第二种情况 对吗?
Because n to the log base 2 of 2
n的log₂2次方
is n to the 1, it is the same,
就是n的一次方 是一样的
so we tack on the extra log n.
所以还有一个附加的lgn
Case 2 of the master theorem.
就是主定理的第二种情况
That is pretty good.
非常好
That says that in the best-case quicksort is going to do well.
也就是说 在最优情况下 快速排序的效率非常高
How about let's suppose the split
如果我们假设分划永远发生在
is always let's say 1/10 : 9/10,
比如1/10:9/10的位置呢
1/10n : 9/10n.
n/10:9n/10
In that case, are we lucky or are we unlucky?
在这种情况下 我们是否幸运呢?
I mean, if the split is really skewed,
也就是说 分划的地方非常的偏斜
we clearly are going to be unlucky,
很显然我们是不幸的
right, because then it's, say, 1 to n.
因为 从1到n
If it is really in the middle n log n.
如果真的在中间分划 结果是nlgn
it is What do you suppose it is if it 9/10?
如果是1/10:9/10
Is that lucky or unlucky?
我们是幸运还是不幸运?
We will have a little democracy here.
我们需要进行一次投票
Who thinks that that is a lucky case?
谁认为这种情况是幸运的?
It is going to be fast running time.
也就是说运行时间会比较快
And who thinks it is an unlucky case?
谁认为这种情况是不幸的?
OK, so we have some brave souls.
好 我们有很多勇士
And who didn't vote? Oh, come on. Come on.
谁没有投票? 来 来 来
It is always better, by the way,
顺便说一下 回答yes或者no
to say yes or no and be right or wrong,
不管正确与否都会更好
because then you have some emotional commitment to it
因为你投入了自己的感情在这个问题上
and we will remember better,
所以我们会记得更牢
rather than just sitting and being quiet.
相比仅仅是坐在那里保持沉默而言
You don't manipulate your own emotions
你们没有调动自己的感情
well enough to remember things well.
就不会印象深刻
Those people who voted win over the people who don't vote,
那些参与投票的人 不管回答的正确与否
whether they are right or wrong.
总比那些沉默的人有收获
Well, let's take a look. Here is the recurrence.
好 我们来看一下 这是递归式
T(n)=T(n/10)+T(9n/10)+theta(n)
T(n)=T(n/10)+T(9n/10)+Θ(n)
And we will assume that this part here
我们假设这部分是
is less than or equal to some cn in order to analyze it.
小于或者等于一个cn的
We will just do a recursion tree for this and see.
我们为这个递归式建立一棵递归树
Here is a recursion tree.
这里是递归树
We have T = cn, T, T.
我们有 T(n) = cn T(n/10) T(9n/10)
Now we have again cn at the top.
现在 我们依然把cn写在最上面
This gets complicated, right?
这很复杂 是吧
This is 1/10cn. Now, over here we have 1/10.
这里是cn/10 这里我们有1/10
And then we are plugging it into the recursion again,
因此我们再一次将其计算进递归式
so we now get T(n/100) and over here we get T(9n/100).
因此我们得到 T(n/100) 和 T(9n/100)
And over here we have now 9/10cn.
在这里 我们得到9cn/10
And that gives us T again.
这里再一次有T(9n/100)
And here we get T.
这里有T(81n/100)
And we keep going on.
我们继续计算
That is equal to cn, 1/10cn here.
这等于 cn 这里是1/10cn
Down this way we have 1/100cn.
下面有1/100cn
And that keeps going down until we get to order 1 down here.
这样继续下去 知道我们到达Θ(1)
And over here we have 9/10cn.
在这里我们有9/10cn
And here, let's see, this is 9/100cn
这里是9/100cn
and this is now 9/100cn and this is 81/100cn.
这里是9/100cn 这里是81/100cn
And these things keep going down until they get down to order 1.
这些计算都进行下去 知道我们达到Θ(1)
But the leaves are not all at uniform depth here, right?
但是这些叶结点并不都在同一深度 对吧?
This side is way further up than this side, right?
这边远高于这边 对吧?
Because here we are only going down by 9/10 each time.
因为在这边每次只下降了9/10
So, in fact, what is the length of this path here?
所以实际上 这条路径的长度是多少?
What is the length of this path down to this,
这条路径到这里的长度是多少?
if I take the left most spine?
如果我们只看最左边的这枝
Somebody raise there hand. Yeah?
有人举手吗? 你
Log base 10 of n.
log₁₀n
Because I am basically cutting down by a factor of 10 each time.
因为我每次减少到1/10
And how long does it take me to reduce it to 1?
我需要多久能到达1?
That is the definition, if you will, of what a log is, log base 10.
这就是以10为底对数的定义
What is this one?
那么这边呢?
What is this path going that way?
这条路径的长度呢?
Log of n. Log base 10/9 of n.
以10/9为底n的对数
Because we're going down by 9/10 each time.
因为我们每次减少9/10
Once again, essentially the definition of n.
再一次很显然 这就是log的定义
And everything in between there is somewhere
所有在这之间的便是
between log base 10 of n and log base 10/9 of n.
在lg10n和lg10/9n之间的
So, everything is in between there.
所有一切都在这之间
Now what I can do is do the trick that we did for mergesort
现在我能做的便和分析归并排序一样
in looking at what the evaluation of this is
观察把这些每一层都加起来的值
That is just cn.
这里就是cn
What is the cost of the next level?
下一层是多少?
Cn.
cn
And what is the cost of the next level?
再下一层呢?
Every level we are still doing the same amount of work.
每一层我们都做了同样份额的工作
And we take that all the way down.
我们把这些都计算出来
And the last levels --
在最后一层
Eventually we hit some point where it is not equal to cn
实际上我们在一些地方并不是cn
where we start getting things that are less than or equal to cn
这时 我们开始获得小于等于cn的值
because some of the leaves start dropping out starting at this level.
这是因为在一些层 叶子便不会继续向下扩展了
Basically this part is going to be log base 10 of n,
基本上 这部分是log10n
and then we start getting things that are less than or equal to cn,
接着计算结果便会小于或者等于cn
and so forth, until finally we get to add it all up.
一直下去 直到我们把它们都加起来
T is going to be less than or equal to cn times,
T(n)将会小于或者等于cn乘以
well, what is the longest that this could possibly be?
最长的路径可能会多长?
Log base 10/9 of n.
log10/9n
Plus we have all of the leaves that we have to add in,
加上所有的这些叶子
but all the leaves together add up to just order n.
但是这些叶子加在一起只有Θ(n)
All the leaves add up to order n, so we have + Theta.
所有这些叶子加在一起只有Θ(n) 所以+Θ(n)
And so this is how much?
这等于多少?
If I add all of this together, what is this asymptotically?
如果我把这些都加在一起 渐近地是多少?
That is n log n.
是nlgn
So, T is actually bounded by n log n.
所以T被界定在nlgn以内
We are lucky. Those people who guessed lucky were right.
我们是幸运的 那些认为我们是幸运的人赢了
9/10 split is asymptotically as good as a 50 : 50 split.
9/10的分划和50:50的分划趋向于同样好
And, in fact, we can lower bound this
事实上 我们可以找到它的下界
by just looking at these things here and discover that,
观察这些项 可以发现
in fact, T is lower bounded by cn log base 10 of n + order n.
事实上 T(n)的下界是cnlog10n+Θ(n)
And so T is lower bounded by also asymptotically n log n.
所以T(n)的下界也渐近为nlgn
So, T is actually Theta .
所以 事实上T(n)=Θ(nlgn)
Now, this is not really proof.
这并不是严格意义上的证明
I generally recommend that you
我建议你们
don't do this kind of thing to do a proof.
不要这样去进行证明
This is a good intuition of a recursion tree.
这只是一个很好的直观理解递归树的例子
The way you prove this is what?
怎么去真正的证明?
Substitution method. Good.
代换法 很好
What you do is use this to get your guess
你需要做的就是使用这些来获得你的假设
and then use substitution method to prove that your guess is right.
使用代换法来证明你的假设成立
It is too easy to make mistakes with this method.
使用这种方法非常容易犯错误
It is very easy to make mistakes.
非常容易犯错误
With the substitution method
使用代换法
it is harder to make mistakes
很难犯错误
because there is just algebra there that you are cranking through.
因为你只涉及了代数运算
It is easier to verify rather than dot, dot, dots
相对于递归树法 代换法更容易证实
and trees that you drew improperly
递归树则有画的不准确
and wrote in wrong amounts and so forth. OK?
数量不对等等问题
So, this is n log n. That's pretty good.
所以是nlgn 结果很好
It is order n log n. And we are lucky.
nlgn的复杂度 很幸运
Now let's try another one.
换一种情况
This is all for intuition
为的是更直观的理解它
because, I will tell you,
我告诉你
by the time we get to the end of this class
当这节课结束时
you folks are going to bolting for the door
你们都会夺门而逃
because we are going to do some good math today, actually.
因为今天涉及很多美妙的数学
It is actually fun math, I think,
我觉得挺有趣的
but it is challenging.
但也有挑战性
If you are not awake,
如果你不清醒
you can still sleep now, but I will tell you when to wake up.
你可以继续睡 该醒时我叫你
One more bit of intuition.
多一些直观上的感觉
Suppose that we alternate steps.
假设我们交替进行
Suppose we do the partitioning thing.
在分划的时候
And it happens that we start out lucky
开始时是幸运的
and then we have a partitioning step that is unlucky
接着的是不幸运的分划
and then we have a step that is lucky
接着又是幸运的分划
and a step that is unlucky
然后是不幸运的
and we do that all the way down the tree.
这样交替下去
Suppose we alternate.
假设如此交替进行
Are we lucky or unlucky if we do that?
这样的话 总体上我们是幸运的吗
This time I want everybody voting.
这次大家都来投票
It doesn't matter what your answer is.
你的答案是什么不重要
Everybody has to have a stake in the game.
每个人都得有个立场
It is sort of like horseracing.
就像赛马一样
If ever you have watched horseracing, it is really boring,
如果看过赛马 你会发现它很无聊
but if you put a little bit of money down,
但如果你押点钱
a little skin in the game
有一些投入
suddenly it is interesting.
突然它就有意思了
The same thing here.
这里一样
I want everybody to put some skin in the game.
我希望每个人都投入进来
Who thinks that this is going to be lucky?
哪些人觉得是幸运的
Who thinks it is going to be unlucky?
哪些人觉得是不幸运的
OK. Who didn't vote?
谁没投票
You guys. No skin in the game, ha?
你们这些家伙 一点都不投入呀
Let's analyze this so we can once again write a recurrence.
我们分析一下 写出它的递归式
On the lucky step, we will have L(n)
幸运的时候
be the running time on a lucky step of size n.
L(n)是规模为n的运行时间
And that is going to be twice.
这是两倍
While the next step is going to be unlucky.
考虑到下一步是不幸运的
It is two unluckies over 2 plus order n.
就是2U(n/2)+Θ(n)
That is our lucky step.
这是幸运的步骤
And then for the unlucky step
不幸运时
it is essentially going to be L of n minus 1,
考虑到下一步是幸运的
it is going to be lucky on the next step, plus order n.
就是L(n-1)+Θ(n)
That is unlucky.
这是不幸运的步骤
See how I have described this behavior
看看我是如何用递归描述了
with a system now of recurrences
我们假设的行为
that are dependent where the boundary cases,
这两个递归式相互依赖
once again which are unstated,
递归边界没有写出来
is that the recurrences have a constant solution with constant input.
它在常数的输入规模里花费常数时间
Now we just do a little bit of algebra using substitution.
现在用代换法做点代数运算
L(n) is then equal to, well,
L(n)等于
I can just plug in, for U(n/2) plug in the value of U(n/2).
替换掉U(n/2)
And that gives me 2(L(n/2–1)+Θ(n))+Θ(n)
得到2(L(n/2–1)+Θ(n))+Θ(n)
See what I did here?
看懂了吗
I simply plugged in, for U(n/2), this recurrence.
用递归式替换掉了U(n/2)
In fact, technically I guess I should have said Θ(n/2)
严格的说 这里是Θ(n/2)
just to make this substitution more straightforward.
这样代换显得更直观
It is the same thing, but just to not skip a step.
结果是一样的 只是没有跳过这一步
That we can now crank through.
现在更进一步
And that is 2L(n/2-1)+,
得到2L(n/2-1)加上
and now I have two Θ(n/2) plus another one,
两个Θ(n/2) 再加上Θ(n)
so all of that is just order n.
加在一起是Θ(n)
And what is the solution to that recurrence?
递归式的结果是多少
n log n
nlgn
Θ(n log n)
Θ(nlgn)
Does everybody see that?
都明白了吗
OK? Θ(n log n)
对的吧 Θ(nlgn)
This is basically just, once again,
我们再一次
master theorem with a little bit of jiggering here.
用到了主定理 除了一点小区别
That minus one is only going to help us, actually,
这个减一其实在主定理中
in the solution of the master theorem.
只会帮助我们
So, it is order n lg n.
综上所述 nlgn
We are lucky.
是幸运的
If we alternate lucky and unlucky, we are lucky.
交替幸运与不幸的分划 总体是幸运的
How can we insure that we are usually lucky?
如何确保我们总是幸运的呢
If I have the input already sorted, I am going to be unlucky.
若输入本身已被排序 那么就糟了
Excuse me?
能再说一遍吗
You could randomly arrange the elements, that is one way.
随机排列序列中的元素 这是一种
What is another way?
另一种呢
That is a perfectly good way, actually.
实际上这是一个相当好的方法
In fact, it is a common thing to do.
也是一个常见的方法
Randomly choose the pivot, OK.
随机选择主元
It turns out those are effectively equivalent,
实际上这两种都是有效的
but we are going to do the randomly choose the pivot
但是这里 我们随机选择主元
because it is a little bit easier to analyze.
因为它更容易分析
But they are effectively equivalent.
但它们都是有效的
That gives us the algorithm called randomized quicksort.
这个算法被称为随机化快速排序
And the nice thing about randomized quicksort is that
这种快排的好处是
the running time is independent of the input ordering.
其运行时间不依赖于输入序列的顺序
Very much for the same reason that if I just scramble the input,
这点和置乱输入序列很像
it would be independent of the input ordering.
算法的效率与输入顺序无关
If I randomly scramble the input
如果我随机的排列输入序列
then it doesn't matter what the order of the input was.
那么输入序列的顺序就无所谓了
Whereas, original quicksort has some slow cases,
然而 原始的快速排序
input sorted or reverse sorted,
在输入顺序或者逆序时则很慢
and some fast cases. In particular,
在其余情况则表现良好
it turns out that if it is random it is going to be pretty fast.
尤其是当输入顺序是随机的时候
If I actually randomly scramble
如果我随机的排列输入
the input or pivot on a random element,
或者是随机的选择主元
it doesn't matter what the input was.
那么输入的顺序就无关紧要
One way of thinking about this is with an adversary.
思考这个问题时 你可想象一个对手
Imagine your adversary,
想象一个对手
you are saying I have a good sorting algorithm
你有一个排序算法
and he says I have a good sorting algorithm
他也有一个排序算法
and you're trying to sell to a single customer.
你们都想把它卖给一个客户
And the customer says OK,
客户说 好吧
you guys come up with benchmarks for each of your algorithms.
你们两个制定比较算法的基准出来
And you get to look at his algorithm.
你观察他的算法
Well, you look and you say oh, he is using quicksort.
发现用的是快速排序
I will just give him something that is already sorted.
你就可以给他已经排好序的序列
That is what you could do to him.
可以这样对付他
If you had quicksort, he would do the same thing to you.
如果你是快速排序 他也会这么对你
So, how can you defeat him?
那你如果打败他
Well, one way is with randomization.
一种方法就是随机化
Big idea in computer science, use random numbers.
计算机科学中的重要概念 随机数
The idea here is if I permute the ordering at random,
如果我随机的排列序列元素
as one suggestion, or I pivot at random places,
或者 随机选取主元
then the input ordering didn't matter.
则输入序列的顺序不影响算法效率
And so there is no bad ordering that he can provide
就不能找到任何一种序列
that is going to make my code run slowly.
让我的代码效率极低
Now, I might get unlucky.
我有时可能不走运
But that is just unlucky in my use of my random-number generator.
但不走运的原因是使用的随机数生成器
It is not unlucky with respect to what the input was.
而不是来自输入
What the input was doesn't matter.
输入是什么无所谓
Everybody follow that?
大家都懂了吗
OK. The nice thing about randomized quicksort is that
随机化快速排序的优点是
it makes no assumptions about the input distribution.
无需对输入序列的分布做任何假设
You don't have to assume that all inputs are equally likely
无需假设输入数据的所有排列是等可能的
because either you can make it that way
因为 要么你可以使它变成那样
or you pivot in a way that makes that effectively whole.
要么随机主元也会使算法总体有效
And, in particular, there is no specific input
具体的说 没有一种特定的输入
that can elicit the worst-case behavior.
会引起最差的运行效率
The worst-case is determined only by a random-number generator.
最差的情况由随机数产生器决定
And, therefore, since it is only
因此 既然它只是
determined by a random-number generator,
由随机数生成器决定
we can essentially bound the unluckiness mathematically.
可以在数学上确定不幸运情况的边界
We can say what are the odds?
确定不幸运情况发生的可能性
So, we are going to analyze this.
现在去分析它
And this is where you know if you belong in this course or not.
现在 你就知道是否适合这门课了
If you have skipped 6.042 or whatever,
如果你跳过6.042没修的话
this is a good place to do the comparison.
这里你可以对照一下自己
Since it is going to be a little bit,
考虑到等会儿有点…
why don't people just stand up for a moment and take a stretch break.
你们站起来放松放松吧
Since this is going to be a nice
等会儿有很多
piece of mathematics we are going to do,
数学方面的内容
you are going to want to feel fresh for it.
你们要做好准备
Stretch break is over.
休息时间到
Analysis.
分析
Good.
好的
I think we are going to make this.
我想应该讲得完
I am sort of racing. There is a lot of stuff to cover today.
讲的比较快 因为今天内容很多
Good.
好的
Let's let T(n) now be the random variable for the runningtime assuming --
令T(n)为运行时间的随机变量 假设…
Wow. I didn't even write here what we did here.
哇 我都没写我们怎么做的
So, we are going to pivot on a random element.
我们要随机选择一个主元
That is the basic scheme we are going to do.
这就是基本的框架
And the way I do that, by the way,
随便说下
is just in the code for partition,
在分划的代码中
rather than partitioning on the first element,
不像之前是把首元素作为主元
before I do the partition,
而是 在分划之前
I just swap the first element with some other element in the array
把首元素与序列中其他一个元素交换
chosen at random, perhaps itself.
被随机选择 也有可能是它们自己
So, they are all equally likely to be pivoted on.
所以它们都有一样的几率被作为主元
And then just run the ordinary partition.
然后再运行传统的分划程序
This is a random variable for running in time assuming,
这是一个随机变量 用来表示运行时间
we have to make an assumption for doing probability,
我们还要做一个假设
the random numbers are independent.
假设这些随机数是独立的
So that when I pivot in one place,
所以当我选择一个元素作为主元时
it is independent of how I pivoted in some other place
与我在运行这个算法的其它情况下
as I am running this algorithm.
选择的主元的事件是独立的
Then, to analyze this, what I am going to do
为了进行分析
is I want to know where we pivoted.
我想知道我们选择哪个元素作为主元
For k = 0, 1, ..., n-1,
让 k = 0, 1, ..., n-1,
let's let, for a particular partition,
在我们选择一个特定分划的情况下
the random variable X_k = 1 if partition generates a k : n-k-1 split,
当产生k:(n-k-1)分划时 随机变量xk=1
and 0 otherwise.
其它分划则为 0
In the partition routine, I am picking
在分划函数中 我选择
a random element to pivot on.
一个随机元素作为主元
And X_k is going to be my random variable that is 1
xk 是一个随机变量 如果它为1
if it generates a split that has k elements on the left side
表示它构造了一个分划 k个元素在主元左边
and n-k-1 elements on the right side of the pivot.
n-k-1个元素在主元右边
Some of those,too, of course
当然有些情况
are n-1 because I also have the pivot.
可能选择到主元导致主元右边有n-1个
And 0 otherwise. So, I now have n random variables
其他情况是0 所以现在有了n个随机变量
that I have defined associated with a single partition
通过单独的一次分划造成了n个相联系的随机变量
where all of them are going to be zero except one of them,
除了一个以外 其它都是0
whichever one happens to occur
不管怎么样
is going to have the value
总有一个变量的值为1
this is called, by the way.
顺便一提
What is the name of this type of random variable?
这种随机变量的名字是什么
Bernoulli. Well, Bernoulli has other assumptions.
Bernoulli Bernoulli有其它的假设
It is an indicator random variable.
这是一个指示器随机变量
It turns out it is Bernoulli, but that's OK.
也可能是Bernoulli的 没关系
It just takes on the value of 0, 1.
它们的值只能为1或者0
And Bernoulli random variables
Bernoulli随机变量
are a particular type of indicator random variable.
是一种特定的指示器随机变量
Which it turns out these are.
但是这些变量
That is an indicator random variable.
是指示器随机变量
Indicator random variables are a good way
指示器随机变量是一个很好的工具
when you are trying to understand
当你试图了解
what the sum of a bunch of things is.
一堆东西的和是什么
It is a good way to break apart your big random variables
它是一个很好的工具来分解一些大的随机变量
into smaller ones that can be analyzed.
将它们分解小 就可以分析它们
Let's just take a look at this indicator random variable.
让我们分析下这个指示器随机变量
What is the expectation of X_k equal to?
xk 的期望值是什么
In other words, what is the probability that I generate a k : n-k-1 split?
换句话说 生成一次k:(n-k-1)分划的概率是多少
X_k is, let's just write out what that means,
我们写一下 什么表示期望
just to refresh people's memory.
来让你们回忆一下
That is 0 times the probability that X_k equals 0
0乘以xk为0的概率
plus 1 times the probability that X_k equals 1,
加上1乘以xk为1的概率
which is equal, well, that is all zero.
这些都是0
That is just equal to the probability that X_k equals 1.
所得的结果就是xk为1的概率
And that is a general property of indicator random variables,
这也是指示器随机变量一个很好的性质
is that their expectation is the probability that they are 1.
就是它们的期望等于它们为1的概率
The nice thing about indicator random variables is
指示器随机变量的优点在于
it directly connects the probability to the
它将概率直接地联系到了期望
expectation without any other terms going on.
而没有产生其它项
What is the probability of X_k equals 1?
xk为1的概率是多少
1/n.
1/n
So, all splits are equally likely.
因为所有分划都是相同概率额
And I have n elements,
我有n个数
so each ones has a 1/n chance of being picked as the pivot.
所以每个数有1/n的几率被选为主元
And, once you pick the pivot,
一旦你选了一个主元
that determines what is on the left and the right and so forth.
就已经决定了哪些数在左边 哪些在右边
So, it is 1/n.
所以概率是1/n
Everybody with me so far?
跟得上吗
More or less?
或多或少跟得上吗
OK. As I say, this is going to test whether you're in the class.
这是一个测试你们有没有走神的方式
If you go home and you study this and you cannot get it,
如果你回家看书还是搞不明白
and you have a deficiency in your math background
那表示你在这门课学习的数学基础有点问题
in trying to take the course, this is a good indication
这很好地表示了这个问题
that probably you have taken something a little over your head.
很可能你选了一些太难的内容
Let's write out what T(n) is equal to here.
我们写一下T(n)等于什么
T(n) is going to be equal to T(o)+T(n-1) + Theta(n) if we 0:n-1 split
如果是0:(n-1)分划 T(n)=T(0)+T(n-1)+Θ(n)
and is equal to T(1)+T(n-2)+ order n if we have a 1 : n-2 split.
而如果是1:(n-2)分划 T(n)=T(1)+T(n-2)+Θ(n)
And now down here it is going to be T(n-1)+T(0)+Θ(n)
到这里就成为 T(n-1)+T(0)+Θ(n)
if we end up with an n-1 : 0 split.
如果是(n-1):0分划即是如此
So, this is our recurrence for T(n).
所以这就是关于T(n)的递归
And, unfortunately, the recurrence is kind of hairy
但是 这个递归有点麻烦
because it has got n cases.
因为它有n种情况
And this is, once again, where the brilliance
所以马上我们就可以看到
of being able to use indicator random variables comes in.
指示器随机变量的优美性了
Because we will be able to take this case analysis
因为我们有能力对这些情况进行分析
and reduce it to mathematics
并且将它规约到数学上
so we don't have cases using indicator random variables.
这样使用指示器随机变量时 就不用考虑这么多情况了
And the way we do that is using the following trick
怎么做呢 就是下面的小技巧
of converting the cases into a summation.
将这么多种情况放到一个累加式里面
Let's just take a look at why these two things are the same.
我们看看为什么这两种东西很像
The indicator random variable is zero,
指示器随机变量一直是0
except if you get the particular split.
除非你们获得了一个特定的分划
Therefore, this summation is going to be zero,
所以 累加式会一直成为0
except for that k which actually appeared
除非这种k分划出现了
in which case it is the value that we say it is.
这样情况下就有了我们说的这个值
See the trick using multiplication
明白了这种
by 0, 1 variable to handle all the cases?
通过相乘0, 1变量处理所有情况的小技巧了吗
I think that is damn clever.
我觉得真聪明
And this is like the classic thing
这就是一种经典的方式
that you do with indicator random variables.
来使用指示器随机变量
It's one of the reasons they are a very powerful method.
这也是它们很有用的原因之一
Because now we actually have a mathematical expression,
因为我们现在用了一个数学表达式
hairy although it may be, for our recurrence.
虽然对于递归来说还是很乱
Now, what we are going to analyze is the expected value of T(n).
现在 我们就来讨论下 T(n)的期望
That is what we want to do.
这就是我们想做的事情
What is the expected value of T(n)?
T(n)的期望值是多少
To do that, I just write the expected value of T(n)
为了计算它 我需要写出T(n)的期望
is equal to the expected value of this big summation.
它等于接下来这个巨大累加式的期望
And now we can go ahead and start to
现在我们就可以开始
evaluate the expected value of that summation.
计算这个累加式的值了
Everybody with me?
都跟上了吗
Yes? Any questions at this point?
有没有什么问题
I see a thumbs up. That's nice to see.
我看到有人竖起了大拇指 不错
But I generally believe that
但是我认为
what I  want to see is no thumbs down.
我真正想看到的是没有人不懂
It is good to see the thumbs up,
能看到竖起大拇指虽然很好
but that means one person understands,
但是那只表示有一个人理解
or thinks he understands.
或者认为他理解了
So, this is, I claim, equal to the following.
所以 这个式子等于以下这些
Actually, I am going to need a little space here
我需要一点空间
so I am going to move the equal sign over a little bit.
我会把等号移动一下
I claim that summation is equal to that.
使这个累加式等于它
This expectation is equal to that summation of expectations.
这个期望等于期望的和
Why is that?
为什么
What are the magic words that justify this step?
是什么性质使这一步成立
Linearity of expectation.
期望的线性叠加性
The expectation of a sum is the sum of the expectations.
期望的和等于和的期望
So, that is linearity of expectation.
这就是期望的线性
I don't need independence for that.
并不需要独立性
That is just always true for expectation of any random variables.
这条性质对于任何随机变量来说 都是对的
The sum of the expectations is the expectation of the sum and vice versa.
期望的和等于和的期望 反之亦然
Here we did the vice versa.
这里我们就是把该性质反过来用的
That is equal to now the sum of k=0 to n-1 of expectation of X_k .
现在它就等于让k=0到n-1求和xk的期望
times the expectation of T of k ...
乘以这个期望
Why is that true?
为什么这个正确
What I have done is I've said the expectation
我刚刚做的表示积的期望
of the product  is the product of theexpectations.
等于期望的积
That is because of independence.
就是因为它的独立性
What is independent of what?
什么独立于什么
The X_k here, random variable,
xk 随机变量
are independent of any of the other partitionings in,
独立于任何其它的分划
if you will, the X_k that would exist for any of the other recursive calls.
也就是说 xk区别于其它递归调用
So, whatever happens in here is independent of what happened there.
所以 这里发生的一切 都独立于递归后的一切
We are actually hiding. Since we have a recurrence,
我们实际上正在对另一个递归调用
we are not partitioning the same wage time.
进行另一次分划
We have a different one.
两次分划之前是不同的
We actually have something going on underneath the mathematics
我们正在关注原理的数学
you have to pay attention to that the mathematics alone
必须注意的是 这个数学
isn't really showing, which is that in T(n) there is actually
其实不难 那个T(n)事实上
a set of random choices that are being made, if you will.
是一系列已经被决定的随机选择
And so you have to understand that those are independent of those,
所以你需要明白这些是相独立的
in which case we can multiple the probabilities of their expectations.
所以我们才能将它们的期望相乘
Is everybody with me?
大家跟上了吗
That is a big one, independence of X_k from other random choices.
这个很重要 使xk与其它随机选择独立
That is equal to now, well, first of all, this is nice.
现在等于这样了 很漂亮
What is the expectation of X_k?
xk的期望是什么
1/n.
1/n
That actually doesn't even belong in the summation.
事实上它并不属于这个累加式
We will just pop it outside.
我们可以将它提出来
I get 1/n times the sum of k=0 to n-1 of expectation of T(k) +
我有了1/n乘以从k=0到n-1的T(k)期望之和
1/n summation k=0 to n-1 of expectation of T(n-k-1)
1/n乘以从k=0到n-1的T(n-k-1)期望之和
summation k=0 to n-1 up to Theta(n).
还有将k=0一直到n-1的Θ(n)之和
That is, again, using linearity of expectation there
这里又一次用到了期望的线性性质
this time to split up these pieces
把这些项拆开
and just factoring out the expectation of k as being 1/n.
提出xk的期望值1/n
Everybody with me still?
大家还能听懂吗
All of this is elementary.
所有的这些都是比较基础的
It is just one of these things that is hard
唯一比较困难的就是
just because there are so many steps.
推导步骤很长
And it takes that you have seen some of this before.
你们以前应该见过这类问题
Now the next observation is that
另一个显而易见的发现是
these two summations are, in fact, identical.
这两个和显然是一样的
They are the same summation, just in a different order.
它们其实是同一个和 只是顺序不同
This is going T0, T1, T2, T3 up to Tn-1.
这个式子从 T₀开始 一直加到Tn-1
This one is going Tn-1, Tn-2, Tn-3 down to T0.
这个是从 Tn-1加到T₀
These are, in fact, equal.
它们实际上是相等的
So, therefore, I have two of them.
所以 现在是它们的2倍
And then what is this term equal to?
那么这部分又等于多少呢
What is that one equal to?
这一项等于什么
Θ(n).
Θ(n)
Let's just see why.
看看这是为什么
The summation of 0 : n of Θ(n) is Θ(n^2) divided by n.
Θ(n)从0到n求和 得到的是Θ(n²)/n
Or, if I want to bring the Θ(n) out, I have
或者把Θ(n)提出来 就是
1 times the summation of k equals 1 to n of Θ or of 1.
1/n乘以n个Θ(n)的和 就是1个Θ(n)
So, once again, you get n, either way of doing it.
所以你得到了Θ(n) 不管用了哪种方法
This is, in some sense, because the summations have
这就是 因为这些和
identical terms, and this is just algebra.
有一样的项 这只是代数知识
Now what we are going to do is do something for technical convenience.
现在我们要做一些使它更简的事
Because we are going to absorb the k=0, 1 terms
我们要把k=0,1时的项吸收到
into the Θ(n) for technical convenience.
Θ(n)中 为了使它更简洁
We have a recurrence here where I have an order n.
我们这里有一个规模是n的递归式
And, if I look at the cases where k=0 or k=1,
假如我们观察 k=0 或 k=1 的情况
I know what the expectation is.
我们就知道它的期望值是多少
For 0, 1, the expected cost is the worst case cost, which is constant.
对于0或1 期望代价就是最坏情况代价 是一个常数
Because I am only solving the problem for a constant size.
因为我们解决的是一个固定规模的问题
And we know that for any of the boundary cases that
我们知道对于任何边界情况
our solution of recurrence, our assumption is that it is constant time.
我们假定递归式的解是一个常数
So, I basically can just take those two terms out.
所以 我就可以将这两项分离出来
And all that does it accumulate some more constant here in the Θ.
这只是让Θ(n)中的常数更大了些
It is going to make the solution of the recurrence a little bit easier.
这将使求解这个递归式稍微简单一点
And, if I do that, I get expectation of T(n)
假如这样 期望值就变成了
2/n summation k=2 to n-1 of expectation of T(k) plus Θ(n).
2/n乘以k从2到n-1的T(k)之和加上Θ(n)
So, all of that work was to derive the recurrence.
所有的这些是为了推导出递归式
And now we have to solve it.
现在我们要求解它
Just to review what we did,
先回顾一下我们都做了什么
we started out with a recurrence which
我们从一个递归式开始
was for the random variable which involved a case statement.
它是关于选择语句中的随机变量的
We converted that into some mathematics
我们把这些转换成数学语言
without the case statement, just with a product,
除去这个条件语句 换成一个积的形式
and then we derived a recurrence for the expectation.
然后我们推导出了期望运行时间的一个递归式
And now we are in the process of trying to solve that recurrence.
现在我们要尝试求解这个递归式
We have done some simplification of the recurrence
我们已经做了一些递归式的化简工作
so that we understand what it is that we are going to solve here.
我们要清楚我们要做什么
By the way, I don't give things like this on quizzes.
顺便说 我不会在测验中给出这样的问题的
I do expect you to understand it.
我想让你们了解这一点
The elements of this you will find on a quiz.
也就是这其中的一部分会出现在测验中
This is a lot of work to figure out.
这其中有许多要解决的问题
This took smart people to do.
留给聪明人来做吧
Even though it is all elementary,
虽然这些都是基础
but working out something like this at the elementary level
但是算出这些基础的东西
is still a bit of work even for somebody
仍然是艰苦的工作
who is knowledgeable in this area.
即使是对于这方面的专家来说
Now we are going to solve that last recurrence over there
现在我们要求解那最后一个递归式
and we are going to prove that the expectation of T(n)
我们要证明T(n)的运行时间期望值
is less than or equal to anlgn for some constant a greater than 0.
小于或等于anlgn 其中a是>0的常数
That is going to be what we are going to do.
这就是我们要解决的问题
And so what technique do you think we should use to prove this?
那么在你看来 我们应该用什么方法来证明呢
Does this look like a master method?
看起来像是主方法吗
It is nothing like the master method.
显然一点也不一样
So, when in doubt do substitution.
所以存疑时采用代换法
It is the grand-daddy of all methods.
它是万法之宗
What we will do is solve the base case
我们要做的就是证明基础情况
by simply choosing a big enough
仅仅通过选择一个足够大的a
so that anlgn is bigger than the expectation of T(n)
使anlgn大于T(n)的期望值
for sufficiently large small n.
对于足够大的较小的n
So, I just pick a to be big enough.
所以只是要选取一个足够大的a
And this is, by the way, why I wanted to
同时 这也就是为什么
exclude 0 and 1 from the recurrence.
我要把0和1从递归式中除去
Because, for example, when n=0, log of 0 is,
比如当n=0时0的对数是
it's like dividing by 0, right, you cannot do it.
就像是0做除数 没有定义
Log of 1 is 0. So here, even if I restricted it to 1,
1的对数是0 所以即使把它限制到1
here I would have a 0, and I can't ever pick a
这里就可能为0所以在这些情况中
a big enough to dominate those cases.
选不出一个足够大的a使它比E[T(n)]大
What I do is I just say look, I just absorb
所以我在前面就说
whatever the cost is into the Θ n for technical convenience.
我们把那两种情况并入Θ(n)中 为了使它更简便
And that lets me address it as
这让我可以说
anlgn to be big enough to handle the base case.
能够选取一个足够大的anlgn处理掉基础情况
So, that is why we made that technical assumption.
这就是为什么我们做出那样的假设
We are going to use a fact
我们将要用到一个事实
which is that the summation of k=2 to n-1 of k lg k
klgk从2到n-1求和
is less than or equal to 1/2n^2 lg n - 1/8n^2.
小于等于(1/2)n²lgn-(1/8)n²
I am going to leave that as an exercise for you to workout.
我想把这留作一个练习让你来完成
I think it is an exercise in the book, too.
我想这也是课本里的一个练习题
I want you to go and evaluate this.
我想要你做出这个
There are two ways to evaluate it.
有两种方法
One is by using purely summations and facts about summations
一种是仅利用和的性质
by splitting the summation into two pieces
把和拆成两部分
and reconstituting it to prove this bound.
然后再重新组合来证明这个上界
The other way is to use the integral method for solving summations.
另一个是利用求和的积分方法
Either way you can prove.
都可以证明
The integral method actually gets you a tighter bound than this.
积分方法实际上提供了一个更紧的上界
This is a basic fact, and you should go off
这是基本事实 你应该去了解
and know how to do that.
知道它是怎么算出来的
Now let's do substitution.
现在我们来做代换
The expectation of T(n) is less than or equal to
T(n)的期望值小于等于
2/n times the summation k=2 to n-1, now we do the substitution
2/n k从2到n-1求和 现在我们做替换
of ak lg k, the smaller values plus Θ(n).
换成aklgk 小一些的值 加上Θ(n)
I might mentioned, by the way, that the hard part of doing this,
我要提到这里的困难部分
it is easy to get the bound without this term,
求出没有这一项的上界是容易的
it is easy to get this bound, 1/2n^2 lg n,
即(1/2)n²lgn
it is harder to get the second order term.
得到第二项稍微困难些
It turns out you need the second order term
显然你需要这第二项
in order to do what we are going to do.
来解决我们这里的问题
You have to be able to subtract a quadratic amount of
你需要分离出一个二次式
the n^2 lgn in order to make this proof work.
从n²lgn中来 进行这个证明
And that is the trickier part in evaluating that summation.
这是求这个和比较棘手的部分
So, we get this.
所以我们得到了这个
That is less than or equal to
这个式子小于等于
Well, I happen to know how much this is by using that formula.
我碰巧从那个公式中知道了这一项等于什么
I use my fact and get 2a/n(1/2nlgn-1/8n^2) + Θ(n).
应用此事实 得到2a/n(1/2nlgn-1/8n²)+Θ(n)
Did I do something wrong?
我哪里做错了吗
There we go.
这里
Very good.
很好
That is equal to -
这个就等于
If I multiply this first part through that is a n lg n.
把第一项乘进去就得到了一个anlgn
And now, so I don't make a mistake,
现在 我没有犯错误
I want to express this as my desired,
这一项是我们想要的
this is what I want it to be, minus a residual.
这是我们想要的形式 减去剩余的项
I am going to write the residual as this part.
我要把剩余的写成这一部分
And so, the way to write that is, that is going to be minus.
因此我们要这样写 这里是一个减号
And then it is going to be this term here,
这一项应该在这里
which is going to be a(n/4) - Θ(n).
它将是a(n/4)-Θ(n)
And that is going to be less than or equal to
这个式子将不大于
an lg n if this part is positive.
anlgn 如果这一部分是正的
And I can make that part positive by picking a big enough a
我可以选取一个足够大的n来使它为正
such that an/4 dominates the constant in the Θ(n) here.
使an/4大于Θ(n)里面的常数
Whatever the constant is here,
不论这里的常数是多少
I can find an a that is big enough
我都可以找到一个足够大的a
so that this term makes this part positive.
使这一部分为正
If a is big enough so that an/4 dominates Θ(n).
如果a足够大 使得an/4>Θ(n)
And so the running time of randomized quicksort is order n lg n.
所以随机化快速排序的时间复杂度的阶是 nlgn
That is what we just proved,
这就是我们刚刚证明的
the expected running time is order n lg n.
期望运行时间的阶就是 nlgn
Now, in practice, quicksort is a great algorithm.
现在 在实践中快速排序是一个很好的算法
It is typically three or more times faster than mergesort.
它通常比归并排序快三倍以上
It doesn't give you the strong guarantee necessarily of mergesort
它不能保证归并排序所能提供的
and being worst-case n lg n.
最坏情况下 nlgn的运行时间
But in practice, if you use randomized quicksort,
但是在实践中 如果应用随机化快排
it is generally as much as three times faster.
总体上来说它会快出三倍以上
It does require code tuning in order to get it up to be that fast.
确实需要一些编码技巧来使它达到那样的速度
You do have to go and coarsen the base cases
你确实需要优化基础情况
and do some other tricks there, but most good sorting algorithms
以及其他的一些技巧 其实大部分好的排序算法
that you will find are based on quicksort.
都是基于快速排序的
Also one of the other reasons it works well is
它很好 另外一个原因就是
because it tends to work well with caches in virtual memory.
它在虚拟内存的缓存中性能比较好
We are not really talking much about caching models and so forth,
我们不想过多地谈论关于缓存模型的内容
big topic these days in algorithms,
这是现今算法领域很大的课题
but it does work very well with caches in virtual memory.
但它确实在虚拟内存的缓存中性能很好
It is another reason that this is a good algorithm to use.
这就是它是一个好算法的另一个理由
Good recitation, by the way, on Friday,
顺便说下 星期五的习题课
We are going to see another n log n time algorithm,
我们将要看另一个nlgn的算法
a very important one in recitation on Friday.
一个非常重要的算法